<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Your awesome title</title>
    <description>&quot;The Goa Foundation is the most well known of Goa’s environmental action groups.&quot;
</description>
    <link>/</link>
    <atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2015 20:12:22 +0530</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2015 20:12:22 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.4.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Final Hearings in Goa Foundation Petition on Goa Marriott commence in High Court</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The appeal filed by the Saligao CCC and the Goa Foundation came up before a three judge bench of the National Green Tribunal (NGT) Delhi, headed by Justice Swatanter Kumar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Goa government pulled out three new affidavits together with a copy of the final NEERI EIA report, which they said, had resulted in a new environment clearance for the project dated 3.3.2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The NGT was not amused when it heard that the environment clearance had been granted without an environment clearance. Goa government argued that the plot acquired for the solid waste site was now declared an industrial area and therefore did not need an environment clearance. This the presiding judge found unacceptable since the environmental impact would have to be evaluated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the original appeal files from the NGT Pune had not yet reached the NGT Delhi, the Tribunal could not pass any order of stay, as pressed for by the appellants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NGT permitted the appellants to amend the appeal memo and file any additional grounds, if required, against the issue of the new environment clearance dated 3.3.2015. Appellants will file the amendments in a week. Thereafter, respondents will have two weeks for filing replies. NGT fixed the matter for final disposal on 20/21 April, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2015 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/2015/02/06/ngt-update.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2015/02/06/ngt-update.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Final Hearings in Goa Foundation Petition on Goa Marriott commence in High Court</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The final hearing of a public interest writ petition filed by the Goa Foundation in the year 1993 against the construction of the Goa Marriott at Miramar, finally commenced in the Goa High Court in February 2015, i.e., 22 years later after the petition was first filed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Goa Foundation had challenged the permissions granted to the hotel, then known as Palm Hotels, on the grounds that it violated the CRZ Notification 1991, being located on the seaward side of the existing construction. As all the permissions from the authorities were post-1991 and the area is demarcated as CRZ II, compliance with the norms under the notification is mandatory. More so as the Supreme Court and High Courts have taken a strict view of violations of the CRZ Notification and directed demolition of structures not in accordance with the CRZ law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Counsel appearing for the Goa Foundation highlighted told the High Court bench comprising Justice F.M. Reis and Justice K.L. Wadane that the land was leased to the Salgaoncars despite the objections of the then Governor of Goa that permitting a hotel in the area would cut off the access of the public to Miramar beach from Youth Hostel. Besides, the huge grove of casuarina trees planted for protection of the beach from erosion would need to be felled. (Ultimately 219 trees were felled to make way for the 5-star.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though the writ petition was filed at primary stage when the first plinth was being laid, the Bombay High Court then refused to stay the construction at that time as the Goa Govt represented that the site was 1.5 km away from the HTL and the CRZ Notification was therefore not applicable. The hotel on the other hand had represented that it was located behind a 10-metre wide road proposed to be constructed along the beach from Yatri Niwas to Youth Hostel. Counsel for Goa Foundation told the Court that both these submissions were highly misleading and grossly incorrect as not only is the site within the CRZ but all other constructions (including Aldeia de Goa) were given a 100m set back as per law during the same period. As for the road. it has never been possible to ever construct such road which was only a paper drawing to favour the hotel and grant it approval. Today, the waters of the Mandovi reach right upto the wall of the hotel on the western side. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The High Court is also perusing the matter in the light of the report of a Commissioner appointed by it in 1997 to report on the location of the hotel vis-a-vis other adjacent structures. Counsel for the Goa Foundation told the Court that the hotel is clearly nearer to the waters than the adjacent structures on either side – Yatri Niwas and Youth Hostel with 100 m and 37 m setbacks respectively – as per the plan produced by the Commissioner. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Submissions by the counsel for the Goa Marriott and the Goa Govt will continue from Monday.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2015 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/2015/02/02/final-hearings-in-goa-marriott-commence.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2015/02/02/final-hearings-in-goa-marriott-commence.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
